we're continuing our introduction to
particle physics and in this video we're
going to study the dra equation Which
models free Spin 1/2 particles in
relativistic quantum mechanics we're not
actually going to solve the direct
equation until the next video in this
video we're going to do a quick
derivation of the direct equation
followed by a deep dive into the
mathematical properties of the direct
equation in particular we're going to
spend a lot of time talking about the
left and right chyal halves of dra
Spinners how they are related to mirror
symmetry how we can project them out
using projectors and how they relate to
dir adjoint Spinners we'll also talk
about conserved currents in the direct
equation and also talk a bit about
matter and
antimatter so ordinary quantum mechanics
is governed by the Schrodinger
equation however the schinger equation
is not a relative IC wave equation
because it treats time and space with
different numbers of derivatives and the
equation also changes form under Loren's
transformations to fix this we can try
deriving a relativistic wave equation
based on the mass energy momentum
relation from special
relativity there are several ways we can
rewrite this it's common to Define
energy e over the speed of light c as
the time component of momentum
PT we can also write the formula in
Array notation using this 4x4 Matrix
called the menovsky metric denoted by
Ada we can also write this in summation
notation if we replace the time XY Z
indices with the numbers 0 1 2
3 we can also replace this sum of the
metric and P with P written using a
lower index
it's also common to omit the summation
symbols because we always know there's a
summation happening when an upper and
lower index match this is called
Einstein
notation finally if we write the for
momentum p as a vector we can write p.p
equal MC all squared if the basis Vector
do products are defined using the
appropriate
signs if we take the mass energy
momentum relation and apply quantization
rules where energy and momentum are
replaced by I bar time a derivative we
get the CL Gordon
equation the Klein Gordon equation is a
relativistic wave equation because the
time and space components have the same
number of derivatives and the equation
does not change form when we do a loren
transformation note that the partial T
notation here indicates a derivative
with respect to C * T which is a
convention commonly used in
relativity we can also start with the
summation version of the relation and
quantize that
instead this gives us a more compact
version of the Klein Gordon
equation as I covered in video 21 the
Klein Gordon equation does not have a
probabilistic interpretation because the
second time derivative allows
probability densities to be negative
which doesn't make
sense Paul dur wanted to fix the Klein
Gordon equation by forcing it to have
only one derivative in time so that it
could represent a meaningful
probabilistic wave
function DirectX idea was to factor the
Klein Gordon equation into two pieces
each with one time
derivative if we start with this
negative version of the Klein Gordon
equation we can begin factoring it as a
different of
squares the square root of -1 can be
handled by using the complex I but it's
not clear what the square root of this
second derivative operator is whatever
this square root was dur wrote it as a
linear sum of first derivatives with
unknown gamma coefficients in
front following this assumption if we
multiply these two linear sums back
together the resulting 16 terms should
match the original derivative
operator this means gamma T must Square
2 + 1 gamma's x y and Zed must Square to
minus one and all the other terms must
go to
zero the simplest way to make all these
extra terms cancel is to make the gamas
anti- commute that is flipping the order
of two different gamas will introduce a
minus
sign this means that the gamma pairs in
the lower triangle here will exactly
cancel with the gamma pairs in this
upper triangle which are all written in
the opposite
order so given all these properties the
gamas cannot be ordinary
scalers they are new symbols which obey
these special algebraic
rules these are the rules for the
Clifford algebra
cl13 also called the space time algebra
which I talked about in videos 11 and
12 if we interpret the four gamas as the
four basis vectors for space time then
the mass energy momentum relation
becomes trivial it just says that P * P
gives the squared length of P which is
MC all
squared if we put all the terms on one
side as seen with the Klein Gordon
equation then factoring it as a
difference of squares is also trivial we
just get p + MC * p minus
MC applying the quantization rules we
get a factored version of the Klein
Gordon
equation if we take the second portion
of this equation and set it to zero we
get the dur
[Music]
equation the Klein Gordon equation is a
relativistic wave equation for a scalar
field and the direct equation is a
relativistic wave equation for a spinner
field here SII is an object called a
direct
spinner and remember the fact that we
have raised and lowered SpaceTime
indices here implies that there's a
summation going on we can also raise and
lower these indices as we please if we
use a summation with the minovsky
metric raising or lowering indices with
this metric basically means leaving the
time component alone and applying minus
signs to all the space
components now now these gamas with
their abstract algebraic properties can
be a bit confusing for people not
familiar with Clifford
algebras it's common to write the gamas
as 4x4 matrices that obey all these
squaring and anti-commutation
rules there are multiple solutions for
what these matrices can be but two
common representations are the dur bases
also called the mass bases and the vile
bases also called the chyal
basis so in Array form the direct
equation looks like
this now this direct spinner has four
components labeled with indices 1
through
4 these spinner indices should not be
confused with the four SpaceTime indices
in this summation over the MU index
which are time XY
Z in many sources it's common to write
SpaceTime indices using Greek letters
and write spinner indices using Latin
letters from the beginning of the
alphabet like AB C so we could denote
the components of this direct spinner
using a lowercase a as the upper
index I'll also mention that in the
chyal basis sometimes the two lower
components of a direct spinner are
written with lower dotted indices I've
already explained in video 9 that this
is notation for parody
Transformations since the direct spinner
is multiplied by these gamma matrices we
should also give the gamma matrices to
spinner indices to help keep track of
their 16
components the first index indicates the
Matrix row and the second index
indicates the Matrix
column so the multiplication between
gamma and the direct spinner can be
written as a summation over spinner
indices like
this however for most of this video I'm
going to suppress spinner indices and
treat the array multiplication as just
being implied by putting the gamas next
to the
Spinners when I said there are multiple
different versions of the gamma matrices
these are really the same objects but
just transformed with a change of
spinner basis so the Matrix components
look different in different spinner
coordinate
systems now with these gamma matrices
some textbooks just treat them as weird
Quantum matrices without any physical
meaning but I want to emphasize that the
gamas are indeed space-time basis
vectors for the time XYZ
directions they are just new versions of
the four space-time basis vectors that
have been upgraded to obey these
Clifford algebra properties
you're probably used to writing
SpaceTime vectors as four component
column vectors like this these column
vectors can be rotated and boosted using
Lorent group matrices applied from the
left often denoted as a capital
Lambda however this is just one
representation for SpaceTime vectors we
could also write 4D SpaceTime vectors in
the form of 2x two matrices which are
just linear combinations of the sigma
matrices here Sigma T is just the 2x two
identity
Matrix these four vectors lorence
transform with double-sided
transformations of SL2 C matrices where
each SL2 C Matrix uses half of the
lorence transformation
angle SL2 C matrixes are often denoted
with L and they are also called spin 13
matrices since they are the double cover
of the lorence group s so
+13 these spin matrices can be written
using trig functions along with pairs of
sigmas for the rotations and individual
sigmas for the
boosts we can write these matrices even
more compactly as exponentials replacing
the trig functions using Oilers
formula there's another 2x2 matrix
representation of four vectors where we
reverse the XY Z directions on the
sigmas using negative
signs this reversal of the space
directions is called a parody
transformation and we'll talk about it
more
later this keeps the rotation matrices
the same since they involve two sigmas
and the negative signs cancel but this
will reverse the boosts since they only
involve one Sigma and so we get a
negative
sign you'll notice that for the case of
the parody flipped transformation matrix
I've written it as l dagger inverse
where the dagger denotes the Herm
Mission conjugate here's
why if we have a rotation in the XY
plane and then do a parody
transformation that sends x y and Zed to
their negative versions then the
rotation is left
unchanged however if we have a boost in
the exter Direction and do a parody
transformation the Boost does appear to
reverse
Direction when we replace L with l
dagger inverse this has the exact
behavior of keeping rotations the same
while reversing
boosts since rotation matrices are
unitary the hermiss conjugate is the
same thing as the inverse this means the
two inverses cancel and the rotation is
unchanged
however boost matrices are hermiss this
means the dagger does nothing and we're
left with only the inverse which
reverses the direction of the
Boost so for Lorent Transformations the
combination of Herm Mission conjugate
and inverse does a parody
transformation because it leaves
rotations unchanged but reverses
boosts now let's get back to the gamma
matrices
the gamma matrices are yet another way
to write four vectors we can write a
four Vector using a linear combination
of gamma matrices just like the standard
four component SpaceTime
Vector the gamma matrices sort of
combine the 2x two Matrix representation
and the parity transformed 2x two
representation together into 4x4
matrices
the reason that this happens is because
the gamma matrices themselves can also
be broken up into 2x two
blocks in the chyal basis gamma T
contains a pair of 2x two identity
blocks and the XY Z gamas contain pairs
of Sigma Matrix
blocks note that the upper sigmas have
positive signs and the lower sigmas have
negative
signs as a result when we use them to
make a SpaceTime Vector we get a pair of
2x two space-time Vector blocks the top
one with positive spatial components and
the bottom one with negative spatial
components transformed by a parody
flip now when it comes to Lorent
Transformations we already know how
these 2x two blocks transform using
double-sided transformations of spin 13
matrices denoted by
l l can be written as the exponential of
Sigma pairs for rotations or
exponentials of individual sigmas for
boosts we can use this knowledge to
deduce how the entire 4x4 Matrix lorence
transforms it turns out we use
double-sided exponentials of gamma pairs
called by
vectors let's see why this
works if we write the gamma vectors in
their block diagonal form we can
consider what all the gamma B vectors
look like as well the bi vectors are
just pairs of gamas multiplied
together if we look at the six main
basis by vectors in
SpaceTime we see in the chyal basis all
the matrices are in Block diagonal
form for pairs of spatial gamas the
matrices have two identical blocks of
Sigma pairs with a negative sign in
front meanwhile a combination of the
time gamma and a spatial gamma gives
blocks with a single Sigma where the top
one has a negative sign and the bottom
one has a positive
sign now sending the spatial XY Z gamas
to their negatives gives us a parody
transformation this ends up being
equivalent to sending the sigmas to
their negative versions
for bi vectors made of two spatial gamas
the matrices are unchanged by parody
transformation since the two negative
signs cancel
out but for the bi vectors made of gamma
T and one spatial gamma a parody
transformation will change the sign in
front of the
matrices this has the effect of
exchanging the top and bottom sigmas in
The
Matrix all of this is useful to knowe
because of the following trick if we
exponentiate a bi Vector made of a pair
of spatial gamas and expand it using
Oilers formula when we write out the
matrices we see that the top block gets
its own Oilers formula and the bottom
block also gets its own Oilers
formula these can each be Rewritten as
their own
exponentials let's call this Matrix
lowercase
Lambda if if we take our 4x4 SpaceTime
vector and do a double-sided
transformation on it with Lambda and
Lambda inverse multiplying all the
Matrix blocks out we get the expected
rotation formulas for each of the 2 by
two Vector blocks that we saw
earlier in this case the upper vector
and lower parity transformed Vector are
rotated in the same
way if we do this again but
exponentiating a by Vector made of gamma
t and a spatial gamma the lowercase
Lambda will contain boosts instead of
rotations with a negative exponential on
top and a positive exponential on the
bottom due to the parody
flip and multiplying out all the Matrix
blocks we get the expected formulas for
boosting the 2x two
vectors note that the top and bottom
vectors boost in opposite directions due
to the parody trans
transformation so all of that might have
been a bit confusing so let's sum it up
when A Spacetime Vector is written as a
column it is lorence transformed with an
S so13 Matrix Capital Lambda from one
side when a space-time Vector is written
as a 2X two Matrix using sigmas it is
lorence transformed with a pair of spin
one three matrices l and l dagger on
either side
When A Spacetime Vector is written as a
4x4 Matrix using gamas it is lorence
transformed with a pair of matrices
lowercase Lambda and lowercase Lambda
inverse these are block diagonal
matrices containing the L
Transformations and the parity
transformed versions of L in the chyro
basis we say lowercase Lambda is the
direct sum of a left spin 13 Matrix and
its parity transformed right right spin
Matrix now all these explanations for
Lorent Transformations involve a lot of
components to keep track of which is
confusing you may want to watch video 12
on spin groups for a more satisfying
interpretation of these exponential
formulas that's based on Geometry and
Clifford
algebras the approach in Clifford
algebras is to start by understanding in
how to reflect an object in a mirror and
then learn that reflecting an object
twice is the same thing as rotating it
or boosting it in the case of
SpaceTime and the rotation angle is
double the angle between the two mirrors
used reflecting a vector in a Clifford
algebra is done with a negative
conjugation
operation conjugation just means
multiplication on either side by an
object object and that object's inverse
for example reflecting a vector along
the Zed Direction involves negative
conjugation by gamma Zed using the
standard Clifford algebra rules it's
easy to prove that this operation leaves
all the other gamas unchanged but will
give gamma Zed a negative sign which is
exactly what we expect for a reflection
along
Zed doing two Reflections in two mirrors
just means doing two negative
conjugations which is really just a
single conjugation with a product of
vectors on either
side using some formula manipulation we
can rewrite these Vector products using
exponentials of a unit by Vector B and
Theta over 2 which is the angle between
the two mirrors this gives a rotation by
angle
Theta if the B Vector B squares to one
we get a rotation just like in the case
of two spatial
gamas if the B Vector B squares 2 + one
we get a boost just like the case of
gamma T and one spatial
gamma now in this video I will write out
a number of formulas involving the gamas
purely
symbolically however I will often use
the chyal representation basis when
talking about chirality and use the mass
representation basis when talking about
matter and
antimatter so we've spent a lot of time
talking about the gamma matrices and how
they are Lorent
transformed now let's get back to the
dur
equation in this video I will frequently
write the direct equation simply using
the four momentum Vector P if you want
the more traditional direct equation you
can always write p as a linear
combination of gamas and then use
quantization rules to replace the
components of p with I * a
derivative so in the direct equation
there are three main objects the four
momentum which is a vector the mass
which is a scalar and sigh which is a
direct
spinner if we move the mass term to the
other side of the equation we see the
direct equation resembles an en value
equation we normally think of igen value
equations as having a Rank 2 linear map
Matrix acting on a rank one column
Vector to produce a rank zero scalar
igen
value but with the direct equation we
have a rank one vector P written as a
matrix acting on a rank 1/2 spinner sigh
written as a column which produces a
rank zero scaler igen value
MC now you might be wondering why I'm
calling Sai a rank 1 half spinner this
is because Spinners transform half as
much as vectors
do now I've shown that A Spacetime
Vector in the 2x two Matrix
representation lorence transforms with a
double-sided transformation of spin 13
matrices I showed in video 9 that we can
Factor this Matrix into a pair of vial
Spinners as a result each vial spinner
transforms using only one spin 13 Matrix
L the parody transformed version of a
vial spinner transforms with L dger
inverse as I showed
earlier a direct spinner is just a vial
spinner and a parody flipped vial
spinner stacked on top of each other
using the direct sum
so direct Spinners transform with a
block diagonal matrix containing l and l
dagger
inverse this is exactly the lowercase
Lambda Matrix we discussed
earlier so let's sum up Lorent
Transformations rank one vectors
transform with two lowercase
lambdas vectors are called rank one
tensors because they have one vector
Index this is not related to the concept
of a matrix's rank that comes up when
discussing linearly independent
columns I call Spinners rank 1/2 because
they transform with only one lowercase
Lambda which is half the transformation
that vectors
get this explains why Spinners rotate
half as much as vectors
do one spinner index is worth half as
much as a vector index
because two spinner indices correspond
to one vector index as seen with the
gamma
matrices rank zero scalers don't
transform at all when we change
coordinates which is why they are called
rank
zero knowing all this it's easy to show
that the direct equation is invariant
under a lorence
transformation to prove this all we do
is lorence trans transform the direct
equation and show that it does not
change we lorence transform the vector p
with Lambda and Lambda inverse on either
side and we Lorent transform the spinner
s with Lambda from the
left here Lambda inverse and Lambda
cancel and if we multiply both sides by
Lambda inverse these both cancel and we
end up with the same original direct
equation
so the direct equation is invariant
under Loren
Transformations the next topic I want to
talk about is called
chirality chirality is a property we
assign to an object when the object is
not equivalent to its mirror image for
example a left hand is not equivalent to
its Mirror Image which is a right hand
transforming a left hand into a right
hand using a mirror reflection is called
a parody
transformation dra Spinners have a
similar chyal property where parody
transforming a left spinner will give us
a right
spinner we've seen that the lowercase
Lambda Matrix that transforms dur
Spinners is in Block diagonal form in
the chyal basis so the top and bottom
halves of direct Spinners transform
independently from each other in the
chyo
basis also we know the two halves rotate
in the same way but boost in opposite
ways so we can exchange the top and
bottom Transformations by doing a parody
transformation flipping the XY Z
directions so that the boosts
reverse for this reason in the chyro
basis we say the top half of a direct
spinner is left chyo and the bottom half
is Right KY
spiral note that the two halves are not
perfect mirror images which is why I use
the different letters SII and fi because
the left and right Spinners generally
have different
components but doing a parity
transformation on a direct spinner
basically swaps the left and right
components in the spinner so that their
roles are
switched if we take gamma 5 which is the
complex I * the 4 gamma
in the chyro basis it looks like this it
is also block diagonal with a negative
identity Matrix in the top block and a
positive identity Matrix in the bottom
block if we apply the gamma 5 Matrix to
a direct spinner where only the left
half is non zero we get the same spinner
times
-1 in other words this Spinner's ion
value under gamma 5 is -1
and if we apply gamma 5 to a direct
spinner where only the right half is
nonzero then we get an igen value of +
one so we now know how to identify the
left and right portions of a direct
spinner when we apply gamma 5 the left
portion will have an IG value of
negative 1 and the right portion will
have an igen value of positive
1 these properties hold in all Matrix
representations for the gamas not just
the
basis using this knowledge we can Define
the left and right projectors PL and
PR if we apply PL to a left IG spinner
the IG value of -1 gives us 1 + 1 = 2
and divided two is just one so the left
half is unchanged by the pl
projector but applying PL to a right IG
spinner the IG value of + one gives us 1
- 1 equal 0 so the right half is removed
by the pl
projector the right projector PR is the
mirror image of pl we reflect the XY Z
gamas which has the effect of giving
gamma 5 the opposite sign as a result PR
projects out to the right igon spinner
instead and sends the left half of the
direct spinner to
zero so the projectors PL and PR are
useful because they let us separate out
the left and right chyal halves of a dra
spinner the key property of a projector
is that a projector will Square to
itself so applying a projector once is
the same thing as applying the projector
multiple
times adding the two projectors together
gives the number one this means that
adding the left and right portions of a
direct spinner back together gives us
the original direct
spinner the left and right projectors
also multiply to give zero which means
they are
orthogonal this means that the left and
right portions of a direct spinner have
nothing in
common when we write out these projector
matrices in the chyal basis all these
properties look pretty obvious if you
look at the matrices for a few
seconds in the mass basis these
properties are still true but they are
less
obvious it's useful to be able to write
out these properties using abstract
symbols instead of matrices because this
shows the properties are always true
regardless of our choice of Matrix
representation next I'm going to
introduce a new way of doing parody
Transformations that will come up later
we know that taking a vector v and doing
a negative conjugation with gamma T will
reflect the vector along the time axis
in other words the time component will
get a negative sign and the space
components will stay the
same now if instead of doing a negative
conjugation with gamma T we do an
ordinary conjugation we get the opposite
the time component stays the same but
the space components all get Negative
signs so conjugation by gamma T is
another way of doing a parity
transformation
this applies for parity transforming
vectors but it also applies for parity
transforming by
vectors if we conjugate both of the
vectors inside a b Vector the inner
parts will cancel so this is the same as
just conjugating the bi Vector
itself in fact if we take an exponential
of a bi vector and conjugate it with
gamma T if we rewrite the exponential as
a cosine Plus plus the bi Vector Time s
we can distribute the gamas on either
side to both
terms the scalar part remains unaffected
since gamma T and Gamma T inverse cancel
but the bi Vector part will be
conjugated and undergo a parity
transformation so this means that parity
transforming an entire exponential is
the same thing as parity transforming
the exponentials
argument when we parity transform a
rotation the rotation remains
unchanged because a spatial rotation
happens in a plane with two spatial
directions but if we parity transform a
boost this does reverse the direction of
the Boost in space as we would
expect here's yet another way of doing a
parody
transformation a direct spinner is just
a left and right vial spinner stacked on
top of each other using the direct
sum so this transforms with a block
diagonal matrix containing l in the
first block and the parody transformed
version L dger inverse in the second
block this 4x4 Matrix that lorence
transforms a direct spinner is denoted
as lowercase
Lambda now taking the Herm Mission
conjugate of Lambda is the same as
taking the Herm Mission conjugate of its
two
blocks and and taking the inverse of a
block diagonal matrix is the same thing
as taking the inverse of its individual
blocks so this means that taking the
hermiss conjugate and inverse of Lambda
swaps the left and right
blocks so Lambda dagger inverse is the
parity transformed version of
Lambda however we know that when we
Lorent transform a direct spinner using
an exponential of a b vector this can
also be parity transformed using
conjugation with gamma
T So to parity transform Lambda we can
either take its dagger inverse or take
its conjugation with gamma T both of
these give the same parity transformed
result after doing a little rearranging
we also get that gamma T Lambda inverse
equals Lambda dagger gamma T we'll use
these fact later when defining the
adjoint of a direct
spinner so now I'm going to explain the
concept of a dra adjoint for a direct
spinner sigh the adjoint spinner is
denoted
SAR SAR is useful because the product of
SAR and Sai will result in a scaler so
this functions as a kind of inner
product for direct
Spinners basically under Lorent
transformation
s will transform with a Lambda from the
left and the adjoint SAR will transform
with Lambda inverse from the right the
Lambda inverse and Lambda cancel leaving
the inner product the same as it was
before the coordinate
transformation before we Define what
this adjoint spinner is let's review the
scalar products for p Spinners and vial
Spinners that we covered in video
9 we know poy Spinners in 3D space are
rotated with su2
matrices which are matrices whose Herm
Mission conjugate denoted with a dagger
equals their
inverse if we have po Spinners Kai and
Kai that transform with an su2 Matrix U
then their product Kai dagger Kai is
unchanged by this transformation because
the ud dagger U term in the middle
cancels to the identity
vile Spinners in SpaceTime are Lorent
transformed with SL2 C matrices which
are not guaranteed to obey the unitary
property this means that if we have vile
Spinners Sai and Fi Fi dagger Sai is not
guaranteed to be
unchanged we can get around this problem
by defining the scalar product to be fi
transpose Epsilon s where Epsilon is
some
Matrix if we Lorent transfer form the
vile spinner using L and demand the
scalar product be unchanged in the new
coordinates this gives us the property
that L transpose Epsilon L equals
Epsilon rearranging this means that we
can turn L transpose into L inverse by
swapping its order with
Epsilon this basically means we can take
F transpose Epsilon to be the left half
of the scalar product which transforms
with L inverse from the right
this gives us an invariant scalar
product as shown in video 9 Epsilon ends
up being this anti- symmetric 2x two
Matrix
here so direct Spinners are like a pair
of vile Spinners and transform with a
left copy of SL2 C summed with a right
copy of SL2 C similar to vial Spinners
we cannot just use fi dagger sigh on a
pair of dire Spinners and expect to get
an invariant scaler since the
transformation matrix Lambda is not
always
unitary instead we'll use a similar
trick as before and introduce a new
Matrix m in the middle so our scalar
product is fi dagger
Ms if we Lorent transform our direct
Spinners using Lambda and demand that
the result is unchanged in the new
coordinate system we get that Lambda
dagger M Lambda must equal m we can take
this formula and multiply both sides on
the left by Lambda dger inverse and
multiply both sides on the right by m
inverse this lets us cancel some M's and
lambdas and we get Lambda dger inverse
equals m Lambda M
inverse but this looks exactly like the
equation we saw a few minutes ago for
parity transforming Lambda using gamma t
what this tells us is that our Matrix m
is exactly gamma
T so our scalar product for Dra Spinners
is fi dagger gamma t
s we can Lorent transform this and use
the properties of gamma T to show that
the scalar product is unchanged after
the coordinate
transformation we Define fi dagger gamma
t as the direct adjoint of the spinner f
I written F
Bar this is like the left half of the
scalar product for Dra
Spinners as we saw before gamma T
basically has the effect of changing
Lambda dagger into Lambda inverse if we
swap its order with gamma T this means
the direct adjoint Spinners transform
with Lambda inverse from the
right now I want to talk a little more
about what this gamma T does to direct
Spinners we know that if we have a left
chyro spinner its ion value under gamma
5 is
-1 however if we apply gamma T to this
left chyro spinner it behaves more like
a right chyro
spinner applying gamma 5 to gamma T
times a left spinner then swapping the
two gamas gives us a negative sign and
the negative -1 ien value cancels with
this to give + one so gamma ttimes a
left chyro spinner has an IG value of +
one just like we'd expect from a right
chyro
spinner now gamma T isn't too special
here the other gamas also have this
property but gamma T is special because
it reverses the direction of
boosts if we boost gamma T times a left
chyro spinner swapping with gamma T has
the effect of reversing the Boost so
this boosts just like a right Cyro
spinner and the opposite is true for
right Cyro Spinners gamma will change
its plus one igen value into a minus one
igen value and also reverse
boosts so gamma T basically exchanges
left and right chyro
Spinners the fact that gamma T swaps the
left and right halves of a direct
spinner becomes more obvious when we
write it as a Matrix in the chyal
basis as a reminder s l is a direct
spinner with only the left half non zero
which I've denoted by two Kai components
here and S R is a direct spinner with
only the right half nonzero which I've
denoted by SII components here the full
direct spinner Sai is the sum of its
left and right
parts the gamma T Matrix in the KY basis
looks like this with 2x two identity
matrices as off diagonal
entries it's obvious that this swaps the
left and right halves Kai and Kai but
it's important to remember that gamma T
swaps the left and right halves in all
Matrix
representations since we've proved it
symbolically without referring to any
specific Matrix
representation next I'm going to talk
about the direct equations served
current we know that SAR s is a scalar
that's invariant in all coordinate
systems but given any vector v the
combination SAR V SI is also a scalar
that's invariant in all coordinate
systems this is easily checked using our
lorence transformation
rules we can use this to Define four
numbers SAR * one of the four gamas time
s
these four values form the four
components of a current density 4 vector
and these components obey a continuity
equation where changes in density of the
time component always result from a
Divergence or convergence in the spatial
current
densities to prove this we start with
the dur equation and expand the vector p
as a linear combination of the gamma
base
vectors then we take the Herm Mission
conjugate of both
sides on the left taking the Herm
Mission conjugate of a product means
writing the product of the Herm mission
conjugates in the reverse
order and on the right mass is a real
scaler so the Herm Mission conjugate
doesn't affect
it now the P components are also scalers
so we can just slide them past the gamas
since the order doesn't matter
now taking the hermiss conjugate of a
gamma Matrix is the same thing as
reversing the spatial gamas so this is a
par
transformation and as we learned a
parity transformation can also be done
with conjugation by gamma
T multiplying both sides by gamma t on
the right we can cancel and slide gamma
T past the scalar P
components now we can replace sagger
gamma t with
SAR this is the adjoint version of the
dur
equation now when we take the adjoint
direct equation and apply quantization
rules when we Herm Mission conjugate the
derivative operator it causes the
derivative to act to the left so I'm
using this left Arrow to remind us of
that and the dagger applied to the
complex I gives us its complex conjugate
which is negative I dividing by I bar we
get this version of the adjoint direct
equation so we have the standard direct
equation which I've divided by IH bar
and the adjoint dir equation we can
multiply the direct equation by sar from
the left and multiply the adjoint direct
equation by S from the
right I'm also going to switch the upper
and lower indices in the summation but
this doesn't change the meaning of the
formula now if we add these two
equations together the mass terms with
opposite signs
cancel if we apply this adjoint
derivative to the left to SAR the result
looks like the result of a product rule
assuming the gamas are
constants so we can undo the product
rule and write the formula as a single
derivative
this proves the four Vector SAR gamma s
obeys a continuity equation and does
indeed represent a conserved current
often written as
J this current can sort of be treated as
a probability density for a one particle
system but in Quantum field Theory this
is treated as a charge density
instead also note that this conserved
current can also be derived using notor
theorem the last thing I'll do is talk a
little bit about matter and
antimatter so we've already seen that
gamma 5 helps identify the left and
right chyal halves of a dir spinner
these are the IG Spinners of gamma 5
with igen values of + one and minus one
and Gamma T swaps the positions of the
left and right igen
Spinners but let's let's consider the
opposite case let's look for igen
Spinners of gamma t with IG values of +
one and
minus1 I'll call these IG Spinners S
Plus and S
minus if we take S Plus gamma T SI and
apply gamma T to it after we distribute
gamma t^ 2 goes to plus1 and we end up
with the original expression this means
S Plus gamma T SI is an igon spinner of
gamma t with IG value + one we'll call
this igon spinner S
Plus similarly if we take s minus gamma
T SI and apply gamma T to it we get the
negative of the original expression so s
minus gamma T SI is an i spinner of
gamma t with igen value
minus1 we'll call this spinner s
minus let's see what these look like as
arrays in the Cyro
basis if we write the left and right
halves of Sai as Kai
andai we know gamma T swaps the left and
right halves so the S Plus ion spinner
has left and right halves that are
equal meanwhile with s minus the top and
bottom halves have equal size but have
opposite
signs we can also show that applying
gamma 5 to s+ makes it look like s minus
with the opposite sign
introduced and it makes s minus look
like S Plus having identical
signs so given a direct spinner sigh we
can either break it up into left and
right halves or plus and minus
halves the left right decomp composition
can be thought of as a linear
combination of these two basis Spinners
which are igen Spinners of gamma 5 this
is the kyal
basis although keep in mind both Kai and
Kai are two component vial Spinners with
the two components representing the spin
up and spin down States so these are
really four component direct Spinners
but we're writing them in this
compressed notation for convenience
the plus minus decomposition can be
thought of as linear combinations of
these two basis Spinners which are igen
Spinners of gamma T this is the mass
basis for the mass basis and its
coefficients I've introduced factors of
1 over the < TK of two for normalization
purposes we'll see in the next video
that the plus component is related to
matter and the minus component is
related to anti imatter so matter and
antimatter are really linear
combinations of left and right chyal
Spinners the change of basis equation
between the components in the chyal
basis and the mass basis is given by
this Matrix
U so changing a column spinner from the
chyro basis to the mass basis is done
with a single-sided transformation with
this Matrix U since the gamas are
space-time vector
changing a gamma Matrix from the chyro
basis Matrix to the mass basis Matrix is
done with a double-sided transformation
with u and U
inverse it turns out that in both the
chyal basis and the mass basis gamas x y
and Zed look the same however gamma T
and Gamma 5 sort of switch
roles we can see in the chyro basis
gamma 5 gives igen value for the top and
bottom halves of the direct spinner
which are the left and right halves and
Gamma T swaps them but in the mass basis
when gamma T gives obvious IG values for
the top and bottom halves of the direct
spinner these are the plus and minus
halves in the new basis and Gamma 5
swaps
them as an aside it's also easy to show
that we can invent plus and minus
projectors with gamma t which project
out the plus and minus halves of a
direct spinner and this works in all
Matrix
representations so to summarize this
video the direct equation is a
relativistic wave equation that we get
when we take the mass energy momentum
relation from special relativity
quantize it and take its square root
which can be done using the algebra
rules from Clifford
algebras Sai ends end up being a dur
spinner the gamas in the dur equation
are a new way of writing the four
space-time basis vectors and they come
from Clifford
algebras four component SpaceTime column
vectors transform with an S so13 Matrix
Capital Lambda from one side 2x two
SpaceTime vectors written with sigmas
transform with a pair of spin 13
matrices Ln l
dagger 4x4 SpaceTime vectors written
with the gamas transform with a pair of
matrices lowercase Lambda and lowercase
Lambda inverse which are direct sums of
a left spin 13 Matrix and a right spin
Matrix we've learned that direct
Spinners can be broken into left and
right chyal halves and we can swap back
and forth between them using a parody
transformation where we reverse the XY Z
directions we also learned other methods
for doing a parody transformation
involving gamma
T we also defined the direct adjoint
spinner which lets us do scalar products
with direct
Spinners and we also used it to define a
conserved current for the dur
equation finally we learned that matter
and antimatter are superpositions of the
left and right chyal parts of a direct
spinner her